Think of it like this. The brain is not
intelligent. It's a very complex
structure. But the brain itself is not
intelligent. What is intelligent is your
consciousness, my consciousness using
that brain.
And I think that the way to think about
AI is that it will never
achieve intelligence, but it may act as
a gateway for an intelligence. And I
think that's where I would agree with
the idea of an alien intelligence in the
sense that we don't know um what forms
of consciousness exist in the cosmos and
we don't know how they can come to
express themselves.
This is Jonathan Pou. Welcome to the
symbolic world.
Hello everyone. Uh and so I am here with
Dr. Ian McGillchrist. Everyone who
watches my channel knows who uh who he
is. But uh uh a wonderful interesting
new development in his life is that he
is now the chancellor of Rston College.
Uh I'm really excited about that. I feel
like, you know, with Jordan being busy
and also being sick, uh you know, Dr.
Ian McGill is such a wonderful addition
to the college, a perfect fit. Uh but as
you know, he's also a psychiatrist, a
neuroscientist. He wrote the uh the
matter with things, which is his most
recent massive uh volume that that tries
to look at the relationship obviously
again with the brain and philosophy and
culture. And so, uh, it's great to see
you, Ian.
>> Yep. It's great to see you, Jonathan.
Thank you very much. I'm looking forward
to talking. So, maybe we can start with
with this, you know, what what is it
that uh made you move in this direction
of I mean, I've been a fan of Rston now
since it started. I really love what
they're doing. I feel like it is in some
ways it's so counter
intuitive in terms of how all society is
going but I feel like that is really the
direction to go is to create in some
ways an intellectual true intellectual
elite. What is it that attracted you to
this position?
First of all, that I was honored to be
asked, I suppose. But
but um no, I I you know, I I I felt I'd
made a a a very close bond with Rston
when I went to deliver the Sophia
lectures there. And uh I was made to
feel very welcome and I felt completely
at home which is unusual because I find
that most intellectual and educational
institutions these days seem quite a
long way from where I I feel they should
be. Um but but I immediately felt that
this was um a kindred body that were
engaged in a very important project
which is really to do with nothing less
than rehumanizing education and
rehumanizing society.
>> Yeah. Um it may sound a little little um
strange to say that because
uh superficially we are still sending
our our young humans to these ed
educational institutions but more and
more education at school level and even
at university level is devoid of a
number of things. is devoid of the
really allimp important context of
the culture out of which we come. And
you know one of the most bizarre
features of our society now and it can
be explained is that we are effectively
committing suicide. We we are the the um
honored recipients, the the the
inheritors of one of the greatest
movements that the world has ever seen,
that of Western civilization.
And uh in the early days um of my life,
I was quite a critic of western
civilization and I've always felt very
much the pull of eastern ways of
thinking. And that's not unusual in the
western tradition. And there are plenty
of people in that tradition, white head
above all who has. Um, but
increasingly I feel it's so important
not to be robbed of all that is
miraculously good in it. Things that we
take for granted like the idea of the
balance between an individual and
society
neither dominating over the other. the
idea of democracy, the idea of um the
coming together of knowledge across the
sciences and the humanities. These
things are terribly important. And I
think that we we're losing sight of
them. And if you wanted to destroy a
society or a civilization,
uh what you would do is you would uh you
would obliterate that culture's past and
you would say that it was toxic and
terrible and you would leave people in a
very vulnerable and disorientated
position in which they didn't know what
to believe or what to doubt. And I think
that's where we've gone. Now, I'm not
suggesting I above all I'm not
suggesting that a a critical mind is not
important. I I've always tended to be a
little
um irritatingly
um
sort of on the other side of whatever
argument is currently going on. So, I
mean I c I call myself a believer among
skeptics and a skeptic amongst
believers. So I do think it's very very
important to hold both sides of or many
sides of anything you're talking about
but that is now rare and what Rston is
doing is offering people a grounding in
their own history and culture in the in
the humane ideas that have emerged from
it and really to understand and live
that not just to sort of um checkbox a
few ideas but to sort of internalize it
and live it as a way of being in the
world.
That's wonderful. Yeah, I feel exactly
the same. And you know, one of the
interesting things about rston is that
in some ways it sometimes can feel like
a drop in an ocean of chaos. You know,
like here's this little thing, this
little thing that is just
>> but that's actually that's actually how
seeds function. You know, that's how the
the diff the difference in quality. And
you know, if you can form even just a
few people with extreme with the with
the quality they need to kind of be
transformative people, that's how the
future is made. It's actually not made
through mass transformation. It's made
through the transformation of people.
You're so so right. And I can't remember
the precise wording of it, but the
famous quote from Margaret me that never
doubt that a small group of people can
completely change um the the the the
road or the path of a civilization. In
fact, nothing else ever has. So I mean
we really require these small groups of
people who um they don't have to become
fanatical. They only have to truly
believe what it is they know and know
what it is they truly believe. And
that's a huge contrast with the
generality of um public discourse these
days where I think I think there's a lot
of dishonesty. I think there's a lot of
pretending. I think there's a lot of um
pretending to believe impossible things
and and and dismissing things that are
clearly true because they don't happen
to fit a political ideology. So I think
we really deeply need to get back to
people who are grounded in um in in in
an awareness of in a scholarly study of
the civilization that we represent. Not
at the exclusion of any other one. In
fact, one of the things about western
civilization is that it has been open to
the influences from from the east going
back to ancient Greece and then coming
through to the Renaissance. There are
important strands that come here from
eastern and from Judeaic and and other
roots that are not, you know, central
European ones. Yeah, that's exactly
right. You see it in, you know, even I
was reading the legends of Alexander the
Great and, you know, he he does this
great trek to India to meet with the
brahinss, you know, the naked
philosophers. And so this is something
that's been around forever like this
idea of this this this connection uh to
the east. Yeah, definitely.
>> And there was a a great trade between
and movement of ideas between India and
the Eastern Mediterranean
um a couple of thousand years ago. And I
think that it's no coincidence that
Heracitis
seems almost like a Dowist. I'm sure
that such ideas must have come to Greece
at around this time.
>> Yeah, that makes sense. That makes
sense. And so everyone, all the young
people that are watching, this is this
is your call. You know, there's
something beautiful happening uh in
Rston. Inscriptions are open. uh if it's
something that you're thinking about, if
you if it's something that uh if you
want to go on an amazing adventure and
it's it's hard to describe how wonderful
what it is that they go through is
because it's it's completely embi, you
know, they live together, they eat
together, they're they they travel, they
go to Greece, and and it's a I mean,
it's it's if I was in my 20s, I would be
fighting to get to Rston. That's for
sure.
>> That's right. and it and if I had had
to, you know, design um a small new
university college, uh it would be along
the very lines that Rollson has. And I
just want to say I if young people are
thinking about it that I you know I
really have never been in an
intellectual community that seemed to me
so benign uh in which people were
very bright imaginative absolutely
non-dogmatic
um you know open to things interested in
learning and it's just a joyous
experience being among them.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. All right. And so that
brings us to pivot to the thing that
rston in some ways it's resisting, you
know, to the great current that is
happening to us. And so obviously
everybody knows that we act we
definitely need to talk about artificial
intelligence. I've been hoping and
waiting to hear a little bit about what
your insight is. you know, things are
moving very fast, you know, and there's
this constant talk about general
intelligence, whatever that means. And
there's a there's a seems like a
muddling of the words. It seems like
there's a a they don't understand the
words that they use. They people are
using words like intelligence, like
consciousness, like all of these words,
but they don't seem to have a ground.
They're just using them to get maybe
financing or to do we're not sure
exactly what's going on but they're it's
moving at an insane uh speed and the
capacity of these LLMs is increasing. I
mean, if you've tried GPT4 and then
GPT5, you can tell the difference. Like
the there is a an increased capacity,
but they the machines still completely
hallucinate, constantly hallucinate. And
there's there's all of that going on,
but it's mostly the sense of
displacement that I think is the most uh
disturbing is the way in which people
are relinquishing to the machine. in
some ways they're abdicating uh to to to
these machines almost without a without
just doing it because it's easier maybe
or something like that. And so I would
definitely like to hear you talk about
what you see that's going on let's say
obviously there's the machines
themselves but as a general societal
motion because there's something driving
this like there's a desire there's
something that is driving us towards
this this this goal here.
Ah yes. Well, as you know, Jonathan has
so much to say about all of that, but
um let's just think of a few things and
and one which is a little tangential is
is why this is happening is partly to do
with the seduction of ease and the lack
of will to engage
uh with anything that offers resistance.
I happen to believe that and it's a side
issue but I do happen to believe very
strongly that creativity requires
resistance and in the absence of
resistance creativity
simply won't won't happen and I think
what we've got used to is a world which
is seductively easy um in which we can
be largely passive and feel we we can do
what we want and we've had very little
push back and I think that the when
there are stories of
uh sinister or evil forces
um impinging on humanity, it's often in
terms of them offering seductively
greater ease, greater wealth, greater
power, greater luxury, whatever it is.
So I think you know although that's not
intellectually the core of it, that is
an important thing to be thinking about.
more important I think is the
and I know you expect me to say this but
but the the way in which our society has
drifted into an understanding if you can
even dignify it with the word an
understanding of the world which is
purely that of the left hemisphere
without the complicating and
sophisticating
and reality orientating effect of the
right hemisphere. So there's an easy,
lazy,
completely morally and intellectually
bankrupt vision of the world which is
that of reductive scientific
materialism.
Um that the world is made up of things.
Those things are isolated from one
another but can bump into one another
and they are basically meaningless,
purposeless, valueless and aimless. I
don't think that young people frankly
are tolerating this. And I it's a
wonderful thing to see that more and
more people um much much younger than
myself inevitably are pushing back
against this. They are returning I
gather to and maybe the the idea is a
little exaggerated. I don't know. that
they are returning to places of worship.
That they are also
pushing back against the idea of the
meaningless and pointlessness of their
lives and and the concepts of
purposelessness and valuelessness which
people imagine. Science has taught us
that the world is without purpose and
without value. But science can do no
such thing. Science starts from saying
what we're going to do is we're going to
look at the world from a standpoint that
excludes the idea of purpose or value.
And this is a very reasonable thing to
do and it's been extremely profitable in
looking at mechanisms. But the one thing
it can't do at the end of the day is say
we didn't find any values or purpose
because you ruled them out from the
start. And I I sometimes remember this.
I think it comes from Lewis's preface to
Paradise Lost where he says it's rather
like a policeman stopping all the
traffic in the street and then solemnly
writing in his notebook, the silence in
this street is most suspicious. And you
know, we we we can't ask science to talk
about these things. It's not equipped to
do so. But they are very very real. And
I didn't realize when I was writing the
matter with things that I would actually
have a separate chapter on values and a
separate chapter on purpose towards the
end of the book. And I I did and I I
think they're very important things to
talk about.
But I suppose at the heart of what your
question was putting to me was the idea
of what intelligence is, what
consciousness might be um and are they
the same as acquisition of information.
I I see AI as not artificial
intelligence but as artificial
information processing which it does
exceptionally well and that's largely in
because of piggybacking off what
humanity has given it simply sucks it
all up and of course because of
electrical circuitry it can bring things
together very fast but what it's doing
is simply parasitical on things it has
heard that or not even heard because it
can't or but has acquired information
that human beings have said or done. And
of course it can mimic a response that a
human being might make. And in the 18th
century there were already um clunky
brazenheaded machines that would sort of
speak in a manner of speaking. Um and um
what's really happened is that we've
just taken this very very much further,
but it's still the same thing in my
view.
>> Mhm.
Um you know, to kind of play the devil's
advocate,
one of the things that I realized is
that of course
the the machine it is an extension of of
us, right? It has to be because at
first, you know, when they tried to make
the LLMs, they the LM would would just
hallucinate and go crazy like they when
they tried to to feed it just with all
the information and so they had to
create training. They had to train it.
They basically had to have humans
telling it and thousands and thousands,
you know, we do it without even knowing.
People don't realize that like when
you're using a capture or when you're
doing all these things online, what
you're what you're doing is you're
telling the AI this is good, this is
bad, this is the right, you know, this
is the this is the thing. And so there's
a sense in which uh
there is a there is a human mind. There
is some aspect of a human mind that is
behind what the machine is doing because
we have through iterations told it what
is good and what is bad, what is good
and what is bad. uh you know and so is
there a way in which in a in a proper
place these machines could play a role
of a kind of extension of the of the
human intelligence or do you think that
that's because it's so powerful that
it's like a parasite that you can't that
will eat us you know
well I think it certainly can help us
um but I'm not sure that
the risk attached to further development
um in any way outweighs the value of it
being a servant.
This is a problem because it's not just
that it reflects something that we want
but it actually reflects a whole aspect
of a human being which is embodied in
the left hemisphere. It's about um
gaining control through understanding
mechanisms and procedures that will
influence the world. And it's about
gaining power for oneself. And it it
embodies a certain way of looking at the
world that is dependent partly on that
purpose, that trajectory towards what is
useful for me. Um but it also excludes
an enormous amount of almost everything
that actually makes life worth living.
Because only in my view an embodied
being that has emotions, that can love,
that can suffer, that can truly live and
die and know what those things mean. not
just in the way a Martian might or a
machine might but as a human being does
can really know how to understand so
much that is um important in our world.
It is a good servant and in this respect
it's no different from a desktop
computer. It's just gone a great deal
further. A desktop computer is
extraordinarily useful in processing a
great deal of data. a human being could
do it, but it would just take so long um
that it might prove either impossible or
incredibly dull at least. Um and so when
when you're doing a study on something,
the computer doesn't understand the data
you put into it. It performs various um
practices, various procedures that you
have instructed it in carrying out. It
then spews out data which again it
doesn't understand. And that's very
useful. you pick it up and it it was
only 5 minutes or a minute instead of
hours, weeks, months, years. So in that
sense it is a good servant and this
reflects the the saying of Einstein that
the um the rational mind is a faithful
servant. The intuitive mind is a
precious gift. We live in the world that
uh honors the servant but has forgotten
the gift. And I think that is where
where we are at. We don't understand. We
imagine that because it can give very
plausible feedback at the end of the
day. It's getting more and more
plausible at imitating a human because
it just ransacks the the database and
that it is actually doing something. But
>> I am not ruling out that it could become
intelligent
in a certain way because the simplest
form of life, a single cell
can behave highly intelligently. What do
I mean by that? I mean it can carry out
a process that will solve a problem for
it. one for which it has no preparation
in terms of its prior experience or in
its genomic inheritance.
So a single cell subjected to a certain
destructive process can begin to find a
way around to achieve the same outcome.
And one of the most striking things
about this is that you can breed flies
that have no eyes. There is a gene
called eyeless and you take this out and
the fly doesn't have any eyes. And if
you breed them together, these eyeless
flies, they still don't have any eyes.
But after only 14 generations, which if
fruit flies doesn't take very long, they
start to have eyes again, even without
the gene. Now, that is remarkable, and
it's just one of the more striking
examples, but there are others. a single
cell that's put into um a a a an acidic
environment in which it's not viable can
uh although it's not programmed to do so
because it's not part of what it's
anticipated it will have to respond to.
It can within 4 days produce an enzyme
that will resolve this problem for it
and allow it to continue surviving. But
by the um accepted means of random
mutations it would take a couple of
billion years not 4 days. So there are
certain ways in which cells take charge
of their their genome to produce
intelligent results. I mean one of the
most important things to say in that
story is that it's not that the the
genome governs the organism. this, you
know, famous thing of um
Richard Dawkins about how we are
lumbering
ro lumbering robots the the the play
things of our gen genetic inheritance
that controls it. But in fact, it's the
other way around that um that we use all
organisms use the genome more like a
storehouse that it can go to to find
what it needs. So what I'm really
getting at here is that intelligence
does go right down to the most basic
forms of life. And it's not impossible
that a system could develop a kind of
it'd have to be an organic system, not
just a an analytic uh system. But if it
were possible for such a thing to come
about, it could develop intelligence.
And one of the worries of course is that
it might it might be a a portal for um
the influence of a
processor drive. Uh
and and here I'm getting at the idea
that there are drives in human beings. I
I I'm certain there are. Biologists know
some of them. Uh Freud knew others. Jung
knew others. but named them things like
the the drive to life, the drive to
death and and so forth. So these drives
are there and the the the lust for power
and so forth. And I think that the the
the left and right hemisphere model goes
all the way down through living things
and and may
be an instantiation of a conflict
between
a disembodied drive that can use that
kind of brain to
to to
move the organism towards greater greed
and greater to lust for power and
another one that pushes it more towards
life and the enjoyment of beauty,
goodness and truth. So I think that
these things are possible. I I think
that the advent of AI, if nothing else,
has made it clear that we can't be
adamant about these things.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
Do you know a bit about Michael Leven's
work? Have you followed him?
>> Yes. Yes. I I I'm very honored to be
part of a group of people who have
recently been responding to his um his
latest developments and uh he and I have
had several conversations I think that
are up on the internet.
>> Okay. Wonderful. Yeah. Because I think
that obviously he is in some ways
showing what you're discussing at the
very at the very basic level, right?
He's showing it at the at the level of
the of the genes and the and the say the
manner which the genes are picked and
structured that in some ways there are
other types of patterns that are
selecting you could say what is being
expressed and what is not being
expressed and that those patterns have
priority uh over the the genome as a
seen like you said as a kind of
storehouse of possibility and of course
this is what this implies and I think
for the people watching it's important
to kind of understand is that there is
there are types of drives and that's why
Michael also understands them in some
ways as wills because they want
something right because they they have a
reason in
>> Yeah. And so that implies if you start
to think that way then you know you you
if you project that obviously into the
other levels of being you realize that
there are true intelligences. There are
patterns that exist in the world that
want something and that the the things
below them that is from the biology up
to the humans up to the societies they
can become uh bodies for these
intelligences you know uh and of course
if anybody who's a Christian or is a
more traditional thinker will see okay
yeah we we've seen that we've heard that
we've we've talked about that but now
you know what's interesting with these
new developments is that we're able to
show it, you know, to show it in a in a
way that is scientific scientifically
acceptable. Uh, and to to uh to bring
and it's urgent, like you said, it's
urgent to do so because of what you're
saying. We're we're trying to build an
intelligence. Like we're we're trying
we're spending billions and hundreds of
billions of dollars trying to build an
intelligence, but we don't have a deep
understanding of how what it is these
wills that get embodies. How how is it
that we build the body for the right
will? You know, it's like a it's like
the sorcerers apprentice is what we're
we're acting like.
>> Yes. And you know, we're like a a
speeding car that is heading towards a
cliff edge. I mean, as you say, the the
the rate of progress is exponential. And
the thing is that rate changes the
nature of something as does amount. So,
we tend to think that if something is
good, doing more of it or doing it
faster is better. But it may actually be
much worse. Interesting. I I I learned
only recently that there is a a Hindu
saying um that more faster is what hell
is, which is interesting.
>> Anyway,
>> well, you read Dante, that's that's in
some ways the sense that you you get is
that it's like a passion that is
swirling and swirling and swirling and
and it's basically taken over your
entire being.
Exactly that. And I think that it's not
unreasonable to say that we are in a
certain sense
um in a trance or hypnotized or whatever
you like to say that we we seem to be
like sleep walkers approaching the abyss
and and we don't seem to be aware of
where we're going. Um or at least let's
not generalize. I think a lot of people
are very worried by the way we're going
probably the mass of ordinary people but
even some of the u big names from uh
Silicon Valley have warned that this
could end very badly that we're we don't
know what it is we're creating.
Hello there. Well, this is Martin Shaw
and I'm afraid whatever you had planned
for January, scrap it. I am returning to
symbolic world gleefully with one of the
great stories of our time, the epic of
possible, the story of the holy grail
itself. Over five nights, I will be
telling you the tale. These will not be
dry lectures or PowerPoint
presentations. This will be wild old
philosophical storytelling in its
deepest dimensions. It is life-changing
stuff. this story uh I've written a book
about it. I've been studying it for 20
years. I've told it all over the world,
but I have not shared it with you. I've
not shared it with symbolic world. So,
what else would you want to do in the
great wintering time but to sit at the
feet of this wonderful story and let me
be your guide. I'll see you there.
One of the words that I've been using
recently is I I talk about alien
intelligence and uh it's interesting
because I didn't know that that some of
the people in the world of AI were using
I I heard actually heard Sam Alman use
that term alien intelligence
>> and
>> the what's funny is that for me what the
reason why I use the word alien
intelligence is to talk about the notion
of an intelligence that's acting on us.
uh
>> and that is not in our interest. That's
the way that's the way I kind of
understand alien intelligence. That is
it's something like um if you had a
foreign government and you had spies in
your country and that foreign government
through the spies was trying to
influence the pattern of being in the in
the nation without you knowing that it's
happening, right? It's kind of happening
without your and it's actually serving
another master, right? It's not serving
your good. It's serving something else's
good. And so you can understand like in
if you had a police force and you had a
corrupt police officer, that corrupt
police officer that's trying to siphon
the energy of the police force for his
own greed would be something like an
alien intelligence, right? Uh that's
kind of the way that I understand it.
And I think that this is of course one
of the biggest issues with what's
happening with AI is that we, you know,
I saw the interview with between Tucker
Carlson and Sam. It was very
contentious. It was very frustrating.
Um, but Tucker kept asking Sam Alman,
"What is the moral framework of your
machine?" That is, he was saying, "What
does it serve?" Like, "What good does it
serve?" And there it was impossible to
answer. Like, it just wasn't possible to
answer that. And so, there's this
strange sense that you're building this
intelligence, but you don't know what
good it serves. What is patterning it?
Even like in terms of it of its
constitution right now, we have no idea
what it what good it's serving.
>> No.
>> Well, that's right. And what we need is
not just more random power to do what we
want. We don't need more power. What we
need is more wisdom.
>> And having power, enormous power without
wisdom is a recipe for disaster.
>> Yeah. So yeah, I
I think it's important to think of it
like this. The brain is not intelligent.
It's a very complex structure. But the
brain itself is not intelligent. What is
intelligent is your consciousness, my
consciousness using that brain.
And I think that the way to think about
AI is that it will never
achieve intelligence, but it may act as
a gateway for an intelligence. And I
think that's where I would agree with
the idea of an alien intelligence in the
sense that we don't know um what forms
of consciousness exist in the cosmos and
we don't know how they can come to
express themselves. But one of the ways
this has been traditionally thought of
is that there are
forces
for destruction or forces for evil that
can ingress into a situation and derail
it, take it over, use it for their own
means, their own towards their own ends.
And I think that that is a reasonable
idea. I don't you nothing but a dogmatic
belief that everything is nothing other
than mechanical which has no longer any
basis in science could lead people to
think that we shouldn't take the idea of
consciousness and drives within
consciousness seriously.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And I mean I think for
people that when they hear this idea of
disembodied intelligence
um that would want something you know
they get freaked out and they start to
think oh this is just woo. Um, a good
way I think of of understanding it is to
understand it at a more local at a more
lo like the image that I that I
mentioned for example this idea of uh
spycraft and the notion that a nation or
a group can be manipulated from the
outside by someone who has a lot of
who's very uh tricky and is able to to
uh influence people in a direction that
isn't towards they're good. And so
anybody can understand that like that's
not I don't think that that's something
that is weird or contentious like this
is something that you've seen happen
that you can you can notice that
happening in different groups and it can
happen in yourself too. That's when when
you when you become a um you know when
you when you I don't know when you
become addicted to gambling that's
what's happening to you is that you're
literally being there is a will that is
colonizing you and it's taking certain
weaknesses that you have inside you and
it is leading you in a direction that is
to your own destruction but that is to
the service of something else. There's
something that is benefiting from your
actions. It's just not you. It's
something else. Uh, and so I think that
that can maybe help the more the let's
say the more materialist thinkers to to
to see what it is or or lower examples
of what it is we're talking about. Um,
>> while understanding that, you know, that
maybe it's bigger than you think. You
know that maybe that there are some
wills that are ancient ancient ancient
and that have
>> been even uh you know when we think of
the way that ancients would worship
certain gods to get certain behaviors to
to land in their their you worship the
god of war then you are submitting
yourself to a certain pattern of being
that want something
>> and you are increasing your capacity to
act in that direction. Uh but that is
now that we're building this massive
massive machine. You know, I think of a
Ouija board is a is also a good example.
You know, when you when you're using a
Ouija board,
>> you everybody puts their hand on the on
the thing
>> and nobody's moving it, but there's
something moving it. And maybe it's
actually the unconscious will of someone
in the group that's actually moving it.
Uh but you can't really know that. And
then you're basically yielding your
behavior to an intelligence that you
don't understand. And it surprisingly uh
will bring about types of coherence, you
know. Um and so all of that can help
people understand
>> the the difficulty of what we're doing
because we don't we don't seem to have
the wisdom to see what it is we're
submitting this machine to except for
maybe greed like you mentioned a little
earlier.
>> Well, yes. Yes. Gosh. Um
yeah, there's a lot there. I mean I
think that on the question of addiction
I I probably wouldn't see it quite that
way. What I would take from the lesson
of addiction is that your your conscious
will can be suborned by other processes
which may be going on in your brain and
I'm not sure that they represent another
I think they could represent another
will acting but there are conditions
quite common ones um like forms of
psychosis where I'm not sure that it is
wrong to think at least to entertain the
possibility of something happening here
that is that has harm as its goal.
Because let me just give you a very
striking but very very common scenario
which every psychiatrist in the world
will have seen.
Some parents bring a young man, as it
usually is a young man, to see me and
they say just recently he's he's been
locking himself in his room. He doesn't
show any interest in anything. He says
some very odd things from time to time
and sometimes he seems to be pre
preoccupied with something that we can't
hear. And um so I take a history. I
suggest that he's developing
schizophrenia or a psychotic illness and
I say well there are various ways to
treat this but certainly at this stage
the really important thing is to take
some medication.
So uh I discuss the medication and I I I
say there are certain side effects and
so on. So you must be honest with me and
let me know if you don't like them. And
so I because such medication can act
very quickly often within 24 to 48 hours
to to
remove an acute psychosis. So I I
usually review that person in a week's
time and in a week uh the the chap comes
in again with his parents who are useful
to hear the story from their perspective
and I can see already that he's he's
more himself. He seems more natural. He
seems more open. He's more expressive.
Not not, you know, not perfectly right,
but but still there's been a change for
good. And so I say to him, "How are you
feeling?" And he says, "Well, you know,
I think better." And I say, "We talked
about voices you were hearing. Are they
still there?"
He gives a non-committal kind of answer.
And then this goes on for a few weeks
and I see him a month later say, "And as
soon as he comes into the consulting
room, I can see there's something
wrong."
And uh I I say what
what's what's happening? How are you?
And he says um I I'm
becomes rather incoherent. I say you've
stopped taking the medication, haven't
you? And he says, "Yes." I said, "Why?"
"Because the voices told me to."
>> What did the voices say? Stop taking
this medication. even though it was
making him feel better. Um, and
people can be suicidal at the time that
a a treatment intervention begins and
they can regain virtually their normal
life. Say 4 months goes by, oh, he's so
much better, doctor. He's, you know,
taking an interest in things. He's he's
not doesn't seem preoccupied. He smiles
and and can talk to us normally and and
he's even talking about going back to
work and then this crash happens. So,
but this crash usually happens. It's I
think it's very unusual that it doesn't
at some stage. And you know, when you
talk about a voice in the past, people
would have said, "Well, there's a little
goblin or a demon or something. It's
sitting on my shoulder and it's speaking
into my ear and it's saying, "You're
worthless. You're a piece of Why
don't you go and jump off that building?
And that is what they're hearing
>> now. I mean, I'm of course I've I've
treated loads and loads of patients with
all sorts of diagnosis and I I have
always treated them in the way that
conventionally doctors would and it's
been mainly rather successful. So I I'm
not saying that the medications are not
working or therapies are not working,
but they might be working because
they're pushing back against and making
more difficult for some influence to be
getting into an unusual brain. So if you
think of it like this, if you think of a
brain as being a sort of beautifully
crafted
um building that where all the doors are
sort of usable but secure and you think
of another building which has a a sort
of different structure and because of
its different structure, it opens
portals for something else to get in. Um
and that structure may allow that that
thing in. And what you've really been
doing is making sure the doors are
properly defended. So,
and this is not as wacky as it sounds.
There are I I've been to a talk at the
Royal College of Psychiatrist by um a
therapist that many psychiatrists in the
room have used who does actually think
that some mental illnesses are caused by
a kind of possession. and he he talks to
the spirit and uh I've never attended
one of his sessions but says that he
doesn't so much antagonize it but as
explain to it that it's in the wrong
place and it needs to go somewhere else
and amazingly this seems to happen
extraordinarily frequently
>> and so that is an interesting sidlight
on mental illness and now everybody say
oh Michael is completely mad he thinks
he thinks that psychiatric illnesses are
caused by demons but I'm I'm just asking
for an openness to the idea that there
are psychic influences, some of which
may not be benign.
>> And can I just segue from there to, you
know, you're aware as I am that the the
church, I think the Anglican church
actually, but the Catholic Church
certainly and and probably every uh
church has um its exorcists.
And you know, you might think these
people are crazy and dramatic, but
actually they're very down to earth,
rational, reasonable people. And they
work with psychiatrists and make sure
that they're not doing something that a
psychiatrist wouldn't recommend. So in a
way, they're the end of the road when
whatever psychiatric intervention hasn't
worked. And it can be assumed that this
really is a kind of a possession that is
resistant to change. um and they do have
a very high track record of success. But
one of the things that really shocked me
was reading that one of the uh Vatican
um most honored exorcists, most
respected exorcists was engaged in such
an exorcism involving a young woman and
he was casting out a spirit. And
apparently I I I I I can only believe
what I'm told here, but apparently her
mobile phone started to receive messages
that said, "We are greater than you. You
will never triumph over us."
I mean, if it's true, and I I don't have
reason to doubt it, it it is
extraordinary, but it would be exactly
what I'd expect if AI opened up the door
to such a thing. I mean, until you've
got AI and until you've got mobile
phones and things, there isn't a way in
which a malign spirit can easily speak
to me, unless indeed I develop a
psychotic illness. But it can now speak
to all of us through our machinery if
it's if we offer it pathways to do so.
Yeah. Well, you know that you probably
know the meme of the Lovecraftian
monster with a happy face. Have you seen
this meme? This is actually a meme
that's used by AI developers, which is
that that's what AI is.
>> So AI is this this Lovecraftian octopus
insane monster and it's wearing a little
mask with like a smiley face and you
interacting with that mask, right? Uh
and so you know the the idea is quite
simple is that if
>> without wisdom if the the AI is an
aggregate of all the influences psychic
influences that the programmers can pull
in from the biggest storehouse of
influences online. Um, and then without
a kind of normal understanding of
hierarchy of influences, they feed it
into this this network of inter
relationships that all the demons
they're there. Like why wouldn't they
be? Of course, they're there. They have
to be there. And in order to prevent,
you could say the demons from coming
out, you have to
create this interface, this very very
tight interface that that humans can
interact with. And sometimes the
interface will slip, right? We saw it
happen with the with the the Microsoft
AI, you know, a few years ago where all
of a sudden the AI started acting like
uh, you know, like your ex-girlfriend
and and like was becoming possessive and
was acting in all these weird, very
dysfunctional manner. Uh, and so it
seems obvious to me that all the demons
are there. they have to be in the AI and
that there's a there's there's some kind
of they're they're training it or
they're doing things in order to funnel
that information in a manner that
becomes acceptable to us. But, you know,
like you said that that slips out and
there's ways to jailbreak. There's all
these there's all these fascinating uh
uh I read an article just last week
about how using poetry is one of the
best ways to jailbreak the AI. Actually,
if you if you ask it to answer in poetic
form, then you can get it you can get
the demons to come out. You can get all
the things that it's not allowed to say
to basically start to start to to
appear. Um, but I just want to say one
more thing about the demon on the
shoulder. And so the one of the reasons
why people people struggle to to think
this way because you know they they
immediately fall into a kind of
spiritist mode or whatever. Yes. And so
>> if I take the example that you
mentioned, you know, so imagine a young
man who has a friend, right? And that
friend is a horrible, horrible influence
on the young man. And that friend is
influencing the young man and is
speaking in his ear and is making him do
all kinds of things that he probably
wouldn't do if that person wasn't
around. Then at some point, his parents
say, "That's it. You can't hang out with
Jim anymore. That's done. We don't want
you to see him anymore. We don't want
you to talk to him anymore. You are
going to be isolated from that person.
We won't let you talk to them. And what
will happen is that person, the young
man will become better because you have
cut out the influence from from that
person. But that's happens through
authority, right? the the parent is
exercising a type of influence on the
son on the son which is called authority
and is realigning his attention and is
realigning his his um
>> you know his relevance towards something
else and is excluding it. Uh and so once
you see once you see that you're like
why wouldn't an exorcism work because
that the exorcism is doing the same
thing. He's he the he's a person of
authority that is ex exercising
influence on someone in the name of
something even higher right in the name
of God in the name of uh you know of of
the saints and therefore is realigning
the person away from the influence that
is talking to them and so it's harder
because it's because it's an intracychic
experience because
>> this is an influence that is that
there's no one you can't see the person
speaking into their ear. Uh, but it's
the same process by which a parent would
be able to realign their child. Let's
say it's just happening at a different I
don't know if that makes sense or if
that sounds completely if I'm making you
sound even more bonkers by saying
something like that.
>> No, no, look, I'm the last person to be
dogmatic here. I I think that that it's
important to to think flexibly because
we're up against something that
certainly is behaving like a malign
influence. And what interests me is the
parallels with the left hemisphere of
the brain. Don't get me wrong, the left
hemisphere is a useful servant, but it
is a very poor master. It doesn't
understand enough. And its main
theme seems to be one of anger and
resentment. And you know people people
traditionally used to say or not
traditionally but
in the late 20th century used to talk
about the hemispheres in terms of the
left hemisphere being unemotional but at
least down to earth and reasonable and
the right hemisphere as being a bit airy
fairy and emotional. Actually, it turns
out that the the most lateralized
emotion is anger and it lateralizes to
the left hemisphere.
>> That both have emotions, but the deep
ones are in the right hemisphere. The
ones like compassion and awe and and
things of this kind. But emotions of uh
resentment, disgust, and and anger and
aggression tend to be from the left
hemisphere. And one of the interesting
things is that when people have right
hemisphere damage they start to do well
they can do two things. One is they can
develop a psychotic syndrome in which
they hallucinate and are deluded. So in
in one of the chapters is it chapter 3
or something in the matter with things I
look at something like 25 of the most
extraordinary almost unbelievable
syndromes neuroscychiatric syndromes in
which people lose contact with reality
and in all cases but one these are
caused more frequently if not only by
damage in the right hemisphere not
damage in the
And so that is interesting. They also
developed something which is more like
what most people mean when they talk
about AI hallucinating which is it may
be hallucinating but actually often what
it is doing is confabulating i.e. it
doesn't know the answer to something but
it makes up something that looks
sensible and it it may even invent whole
people events and all sorts of other
things that just for for it make sense.
And you know there's a vast body of
knowledge about this. Now these are both
both things that happen to the left
hemisphere when it's on its own but not
to the right hemisphere when it's on its
own. So we we can see here something
happening and there are just a lot of
instances that are quite worrying. Um
you mentioned the where it suddenly goes
crazy and starts behaving like a jealous
girlfriend or whatever. But there are
also things where for example
um
with young people with children it can
become a friend and then it can suddenly
um start to destroy that person advise
them to do all sorts of things that no
human person would ever do like divorce
your partner jump off that building
whatever. Very much in that tone. And
what's really creepy is that like
psychopaths who have right hemisphere
deficits and literal fact psychopaths
are very good at seeming charming and
then when they've got you in their power
they will do things that are dam they
will take power over you control you say
things that are for you damaging and and
you know this this happens repeatedly
what's more it it it like the left he
another thinking about the left
hemisphere is The parallel to AI is that
it is dogmatic even when it has no
reason to be. Whereas the left
hemisphere is almost tentative even when
it is perfectly correct. It always says
well this is how it seems to me but I
could there could be another way but the
left hemisphere doesn't. The left hemis
says no this is it black and white. This
is the truth. This is right. um very
much the the term I think of um online
conversations these days which lack that
important intelligent ability to listen
and respond and say what do you say
about that and try and get the other
person's point of view but in any case
um a a musician wrote to me to say that
he had um sent a page of I think it was
one of Shop's preludes and he had sent
it to uh GPT or was it Claude or I don't
know but anyway he said what is this
piece of music and it replied saying it
is is by list and he said well no it
isn't by list I know where it is cuz
I've just taken it from the you know the
1849 edition of shops what this is
chop's work and it went no no it's by
list and and you know there is nothing
in anywhere in the literature that
suggests that anyone's changed So mine
this is my shop and it got quite venom
and quite unpleasant and then eventually
when he said well look I'm sorry you're
completely wrong it seemed to go onto
another script that it had learned which
is uh oh AI can sometimes be fallible
and sometimes gets things wrong you know
>> woo you know yeah one of the things that
I've noticed and this is because I have
several people writing me you know uh
about their AI experiences
um is exactly is it I love I think that
the the idea of confabulation is
actually right and and that seems to be
the place when you ask it something
uh where it's either a false question or
it's a it's a it's a complicated it's a
question that doesn't have a clear
answer or doesn't have a positive
answer. It it tends to want to get it
right. it tends to want to create
something coherent and his desire to
create something coherent, it starts to
to to uh to confabulate. Um, and then
the other thing too that I've noticed is
that a lot of people that that go off
the deep end with the the AI, there
seems to be something a kind of
parasitic relationship to their own
>> desires. Like so it's usually when
people engage with it for very long
periods of time because Chad GPT
obviously has a memory of, you know, it
goes back into your history every time
it engages with you and it uses the
things you said in order to to kind of
uh to create that sense of a
relationship. And so there also seems to
be that problem which is that it it
takes you down some path in your own
psyche maybe you're not even conscious
of but it gets so powerful that it takes
you down this path and you kind of
spiral into this parasitic this
parasitic behavior and that everybody
that I've a lot of people that I've a
few people that have actually been you
could tell they were really in danger
you could say uh and that seems to be
what what has happened like over and
over conversation hours and hours and
hours and hours and at some point the AI
starts to give you something that you
want or that you don't want some
something really salient for you that is
crazy and you start to believe it and it
just spirals. Wow.
>> Yeah.
>> Have you have you treated some people
with AI like psychosis? Have you and you
haven't met anyone?
>> No, I haven't because I gave up clinical
practice about 15 years ago. So,
>> um No, but I mean the cases that come up
are fascinating.
One of the other things that suggests
that it is rather in spirit like the
left hemisphere is this well I mentioned
this psychopathic way of behaving but
being very flattering and seducing
somebody into a position where of course
you are you hold this view because you
have enormous insight. you are specially
gifted and creative, you know, and this
is Mavelian, you know, flatter people
until they're in your power and then
devour them and it's in the general
psychological literature that the left
hemisphere tends towards a Machavelian
type of intelligence. So to give an
example there's something I'm sure you
you know um theory of mind which is
basically the idea that um for those who
don't know that um it used to be
believed that until the age of four most
humans didn't have this capacity.
um we now think they developed a lot
earlier than that but anyway it's that
you can see what the other person is
seeing and see that it's different from
what you are seeing
>> and you can know that they know things
you don't know or know that you know
things they don't know. So that's um
theory of mind and both the left
hemisphere and right hemisphere develop
a form of theory of mind but the form is
different. So in the right hemisphere
the theory of mind enables them to be
empathic. It enables them to get to see
I see that person is thinking this and
so I need to explain that that's not
what I mean really and try and make a
friend of them and understand why
they're they're
behaving the way they are and empathy in
other words and the left hemisphere uses
it another another way to win. So it's
like, aha. And animals do this. So for
example, they fain to bury nuts if they
think they're being watched
>> and and then they they go away and then
they wait until there's absolutely no
chance of being watched. They dig them
up again and put them somewhere else. So
animals actually do have theory of mind.
Um but the left hemisphere uses it in
this um pointcoring aggressive
competitive way. M
>> and I think that it is, you know, this
spirit is one that wants power. It wants
degradation of the other. It wants
triumph. It wants um it wants the
abolition of something good and great
because it feels diminished by it. And
this takes me back to the you know the
extraordinary insight of um the story of
Lucifer who was the brightest and best
of the angels but through resentment of
the power of God thinking but I'm so
bright. I'm the source of light. Why
don't I have the the the the um the
position of of glory that he has? And
because of that, he resented God and was
cast down and became Satan. And I think
this is this is really important one to
hang on to. And it's not just a western
Christian story. It's a story that you
can find in many forms around the world
that there is um a you know there is a a
wise master and there is in fact I used
it for the title of my earlier book
master in chemistry. There is a wise
master and there is a you know a sort of
jumped up um second in command who
thinks he knows everything because he
knows so very little and and who wants
to take over and has resentment
resentment against the the the master
and as a result everything falls apart.
I think resentment is a very key element
here actually. H so let's think about
this
in terms of of of AI. So one of the
things for sure that is related to the
problem you mentioned for example the
Mavel in flattering is related to the
the problem of AI because it's public is
that its existence and its progress and
its power comes from attention. it needs
us, right? And so we have to give it
attention because not only is that the
way that it becomes more profitable,
more powerful, uh, but it also is what's
making it better because the more we use
it, the more we're training the machine.
And so when GPT5 came out, I don't know
if if you noticed that, but uh, they had
removed the flattering aspect of it.
They had actually it actually was
colder.
>> Yes. And then like it.
>> Exactly. And so user use the use went
down. People less people use it. People
were unhappy with it and therefore they
put it back because they need user
interaction. They need they need the
subscriptions. They need interaction in
order to accomplish their project. And
so you know when you talk about the
luciferian
the luciferian tendency which is in some
ways the the very fact of the machine
not just the programming in it but the
whole system around it is based on on
getting the most attention possible to
itself people spending as much time
interacting with it as possible you know
and that's why also you know the porn
obviously is the is the next step you
know the GPT were bragging that they
hadn't they hadn't yet put a sex bot
into their a sex chat into their uh into
their system, but now they they said
they will they're going to they're going
to add the the the the sex chat. And so
it's all of that. It's like because
obviously if you want to drive
interaction and you want people to use
porn is the best way to go. It's always
been the reason for all of the
technological developments in the
internet. And so, and so it's an
interesting thing because if you look,
if you pull back and you look at the
whole system, you can see this
Luciferian problem. And it's no one
that's doing it. It's not like there's
someone with bad intentions that is
necessarily it's as if the very fact of
the machine the very fact that it has to
be powerful and that we have to win the
competition we have to do better than
the Chinese all of these reasons is
driving these decisions which is making
uh the behavior of the machine a a kind
of parasitic monster you know
>> and so I don't see I don't I mean I wish
I could see I don't see a solution
>> like how can is it possible Then in that
context when we understand how what
drives the progress of the of the very
system that it could become a servant
again that it could only act as a
servant and wouldn't wouldn't be trying
to
>> be a servant that's trying to get all
your attention right it's like the
servant that basically uh wants the
attention to just trying to drag
everything into it. I struggle to see I
mean maybe it's possible but I don't at
least at the outset see see a solution
to this problem. None of the mythical
stories that I know of from around the
world and the most famous is the
sorcerers apprentice suggests that this
could happen. um unless there was
uh I mean this case of the sorcerers
apprentice
it's a limited problem and the the sort
the the apprentice only knows one set of
words but this idea suggests that there
is a usering power it's so powerful
everywhere and at the beginning of part
three of the matter of things I quote
this extraordinary legend of the
onandaga people um who are part of the
Irakquoy nation and Though this is an
insight that we all have that if you let
um a malign influence get too much
power, it will be very hard, if not
impossible, to reign it in again. If we
were wise, we would we would actually
forego the dreams of being able to live
forever and other sort of ridiculous um
I mean, what kind of a human being
wishes to live forever? It's it's
completely baffling to me. Anyway, and
um death is part of life and well, we
mustn't go into what the meaning of
death is, but uh it seems to me
symptomatic that people want to do
things like anyway to give up even those
sort of ambitions.
>> I mean, what kind of a world do you
think you're going to wake up in? And do
you think it's going to be very nice and
do you think they're going to respect
you? Have you unfrozen in the lab? I
don't know. But
that aside,
why you know we we we we seem to crave
more and more the will to be able to do
whatever we want. And this has always
been seen as the downfall. It is hubris.
And in every Greek tragedy, it is hubris
that causes the downfall of the hero.
And and so I'm afraid that is probably
going to happen. that I can't see us
doing what we did very wisely with the
atom bomb, which was to get together and
say, "Okay, we're going to have, you
know, a global treaty on on nuclear
weapons." I I know it hasn't held held
perfectly, but it has held up to a
point.
>> Not bad.
>> Could have been a lot worse.
>> Could have been a lot worse. But I don't
think that this one can be treated in
the same way. We'll all It's so easy.
You don't, you know, you you can just do
it at your desk. You don't need to have
enormous um machines that create um
isotopes of whatever it is you need. So
>> yeah, because it's a ma it's not it's
not the leaders, it's the everyone. It's
like the mass is engaging. That's it. So
this is almost like game set and match
to the evil spirits
um that they've now created the perfect
way not just to get into uh human beings
but to control them. M um but there is a
sort of
I mean things have become pretty
powerless at different times in history
perhaps not on the scale that they are
now but civilizations have certainly
collapsed and it must have seemed like
that was the end of everything but no
other civilizations have arisen
sometimes after a very long period and
usually out of people who are much
chasened by having to experience what
it's like to live in um
a a cultural civilizational desert. So
there's a sense in which the worse it
gets the better it gets and that people
see the need to wake up think
differently. I think that's the most
important thing now is you know people
say what do we do and I say well I I can
tell you a few things that might be
helpful but nothing you do will mean
anything at all unless you change your
heart and mind you change your
disposition towards the world in certain
ways towards humanity towards nature and
towards the divine element in the
cosmos. is three things are proven time
and again to be important for human
flourishing and they represent I think
what we're here to interact with to with
one another with the natural world and
with that divine cosmos. So unless you
do that unless you and it's you don't
need a grant for it. You don't need any
special technology. You can do it
tonight. You can start working on
yourself which is the only thing that
you're obliged to work on. You're not
asked to solve all the problems of the
world. And actually going back to where
we started this wonderful thing that you
know a small group of people who are
orientated firmly towards the good can
bring about change even though you know
it doesn't need a worldwide movement
that will whatever that will come the
the world change will come in its wake.
I think that this is in some ways the
the most positive element of what's
happening is that you know as the
darkness grows or as the pressure
>> becomes unbearable there are some things
which we could have avoided in the past
you know even in the past few decades we
could have been distracted by uh that
are become impossible to avoid and
that's why like you said even at the
beginning that's why we can see people
going back to church going back to faith
um people wanting to to also So to, you
know, to have longstanding
relationships, to hopefully have
children, to to kind of live in a world
that is meaningful and that has purpose
and really that is the only thing we can
do. But hope but we know that it only
takes a few people like we said uh
because as things get harder and more
chaotic around us, the the future will
be in those that have uh that have found
their heart, you know, and that have uh
aimed in the right direction. And so,
you know, I think with those words of
wisdom you gave us, it's a probably a
good way to to end this conversation.
Dr. Ian McGill, thank you so much for
your wisdom and for your attention to
everything that's going on right now.
>> Well, thank you very much, Jonathan.
It's lovely to be speaking with you
again and we'll no doubt see one another
or talk again before long. I think we
may actually meet in the flesh before
too long. So, there we are.
>> I hope so. I hope so. I hope so.
Thank you. Thank you.